+55 (61) 99164-3843 Brasília, DF

cayanportela@hotmail.com

Cayan Portela

Data Scientist

GitHub: cayan-portela LinkedIn: cayan-portela

With over 5 years of experience in data science, statistics and quantitative finance, working in large companies. PhD candidate in Quantitative Finance, researching machine learning models for probability of default, which adhere to current regulations (e.g., IFRS9). Experience in analyzing structured and unstructured data and solving business problems using data-driven techniques. Acting in process improvement, which results in task optimization, cost reduction and increased productivity.

SKILLS

Tools and Languages

R, Python, SAS, SQL, GCP

Quantitative Research

Machine Learning, Statistical Modeling, Probability Theory

Communication English, C2 (EF SET 78/100)

EXPERIENCE

Bank of Brazil

Senior Data Scientist / globoplay (streaming platform) Globo

2022 - current

Remote

Growth Hacking: extracting insights focused on retention and acquisition metrics, leveraging business strategy.

Next Best Offer: development of a supervised model to offer the best next product for each customer.

Data Scientist / Investment Division

2019 - 2022

Brasília

- Development of churn models, identifying customers with probability of evasion.
- Risk sensitivity analysis in investors portfolios.
- Automation of simulation models, providing pessimistic and optimistic scenarios forecasts.
- Implementation of external information via API and web-scrapping.

Volunteer professor

University of Brasília, UnB

2019 - current Brasília

- Contemporary Topics in Finance Data Science. • Quantitative Methods and Models for Decision Making (2019/1).

Statistician / Innovation, Regulation, Infrastructure and Credit Studies

2017 — current

Brasília

- Econometric and quasi-experimental models for causal effect.
- Supervised and unsupervised machine learning methods.
- · Analysis of financial system indicators.

Institute of Applied Economic Research, IPEA

Data visualization (interactive and static) and external data collection.

Data scientist / Researcher 2017 — current

Machine Learning Laboratory in Finance and Organizations

Brasília

- Unprecedented studies and research using machine learning applications.
- Consulting for interactive data visualization panel development.
- Delivering courses focused on data science and statistical computing.

EDUCATION

PhD candidate, Finance and Quantitative Methods, University of Brasília, Current

Thesis topic: Dynamic Estimates of Probability of Default with Survival Analysis and Machine Learning

Msc, Experimental Statistics, University of São Paulo

2018

2015

PUBLICATIONS

Feature selection and deep neural networks for stock price direction forecasting using technical analysis indicators Machine Learning with Applications, 100060, (2021)

Application of Machine Learning Ensemble Techniques in the Banking Industry

CFA Society Brazil, Honorable mention (2020)

Bachelor, Statistics, University of Brasília

The robot from Ipanema goes working: estimating the probability of jobs automation in Brazil

Latin American Business Review, 20.3, (2019)

Probability of automation of Brazilian occupations and Industry 4.0

https://lamfo.shinyapps.io/automacao

Published at Folha de São Paulo, Época Negócios and others.